<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pages |</title><link>/page/</link><atom:link href="/page/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Pages</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 21:22:57 -0400</lastBuildDate><image><url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>Pages</title><link>/page/</link></image><item><title>For Prospective Students</title><link>/page/for-prospective-students/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 21:22:57 -0400</pubDate><guid>/page/for-prospective-students/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>This page is a work in progress, but as application season is coming up, I wanted to put this out there! Updates forthcoming.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I often receive emails from students who are wondering whether they should pursue medical school, a PhD in anthropology, or both. Because I often have these conversations, I have a sense that there is a dearth of information out there about this career path despite a growing interest in it. This page is an attempt to collect some of my thoughts about dual careers in medicine and anthropology. My thoughts on this are certainly neither exhaustive nor sufficient, but I hope this is one of many resources you can consider as you think about whether to embark upon this path. The other resource I would recommend is the list of physician-scientist programs in anthropology, which you can find
&lt;a href="https://physicianscientists.site-ym.com/page/SSH" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>. While the list is always changing, this will give you a good starting place from which to see what schools you might consider attending should you want dual training.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here are some answers to the questions that people ask me about this path:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Should I get an MD/PhD in anthropology? Is it a good idea? Is it worth all the time?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By the time you talk to someone in my position, they will likely have a polished answer to this question, giving you the impression that MD/PhD anthropology students were always certain that this is what they wanted to do. While this might be the case for some people, it certainly wasn&amp;rsquo;t the case for me. Deciding to do this was complicated, and at least for me, involved a lot of uncertainty. Here are some questions I normally pose to students when they ask me whether this is the right fit for them:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>What kind of research do you want to do? Which discipline asks the questions you like to ask and answers them in a way that excites you? (&lt;em>Is it possible that you prefer similar &amp;ndash; but different! &amp;ndash; disciplines like public health, health policy, or bioethics?&lt;/em>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Do you want to see patients, or would you be happy if you worked in the sphere of health? Do you want to be a clinician, researcher, or both?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What are your personal life goals? In ten years, what things would have to be true in order for you to be happy?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Graduate school and medical school, in most places, will be very culturally different. Do you prefer your time to be structured by other people or by yourself? Do you feel flexible about switching between the two?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What kinds of skills will you need to do the things that you want? What are your strengths, and where do you have room for growth?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What specialties are you interested in? Are these specialties traditionally ones which allow for robust careers in research?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What kinds of financial resources do you have, and what are your financial goals? Are they compatible with an extended period living on a graduate student salary? What benefits do your prospective programs offer?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The answer to these questions can absolutely be &lt;em>I don&amp;rsquo;t know!&lt;/em> but they are starting points for reflection about what might be right for you. I also often suggest to students that they take a period of time to read from different fields and ask themselves what kinds of scholarship they enjoy reading. Books? Short articles? Qualitative or quantitative work? Research papers or advocacy? Journalism or scholarship? Remember that enjoying reading a particular kind of scholarship is not the same as wanting to produce it, so thinking about the process of research in different fields and whether it suits you can be important as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ultimately, I love being an anthropologist, and I would highly recommend training in anthropology. If you need to talk through whether it&amp;rsquo;s right for you &amp;ndash; and whether a dual career makes sense for your goals &amp;ndash; reaching out to mentors who are faculty that you admire and students you hope to emulate is a great first start.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Do you think I&amp;rsquo;m competitive for programs?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I sincerely wish I knew the answer to this, but being competitive for these programs is multi-factorial. I&amp;rsquo;m happy to talk through your concerns with you and establish a plan for getting you towards your goals.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Where do you recommend I look for community and mentorship?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a first step, I highly recommend that, if you are able, you attend the National Conference for
&lt;a href="http://shssmconference.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Physician-Scholars in the Social Sciences and Humanities&lt;/a>. Every other year, trainees and faculty gather to discuss research &amp;amp; strengthen our community. While there is strong representation from anthropology and history, each year an increasing number of sociologists, public health scholars, epidemiologists, and other social scientists or humanists attend. If you are unable to make it, one resource which could show you the diversity of careers and research are the programs from prior years of the conference. Through the lists of presentations, you are likely to find scholars doing work that&amp;rsquo;s interesting to you and it may point you to people and institutions that share your interests.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Trauma &amp; Inheritance</title><link>/page/trauma-and-inheritance/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 16:04:31 -0400</pubDate><guid>/page/trauma-and-inheritance/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Human Rights &amp; Medicine</title><link>/page/human-rights-and-medicine/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 16:04:19 -0400</pubDate><guid>/page/human-rights-and-medicine/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have ongoing interests in human rights, humanitarian practice, and medicine. I previously served as the co-chair of the
&lt;a href="https://www.phrstudents.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Physicians for Human Rights Student Advisory Board&lt;/a>. I have also worked with the Philadelphia Human Rights Clinic, Doctors 4 Camp Closure, and Doctors for America on projects related to human rights.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I have written on topics in human rights as a member of the advocacy committee on the student advisory board for Physicians for Human Rights. You can see some of that work
&lt;a href="https://www.phrstudents.com/post/2020/03/31/close-the-camps-in-the-time-of-covid-19" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a> and
&lt;a href="https://www.phrstudents.com/post/2018/11/27/act-now-the-proposed-public-charge-rule" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Back to
&lt;a href="/page/my-work/">my work&amp;hellip;&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Health Equity &amp; Medical Education</title><link>/page/health-equity-medical-education/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 16:04:07 -0400</pubDate><guid>/page/health-equity-medical-education/</guid><description>&lt;p>I also have interests in health equity and medical education. Previously, I have helped direct a core course in social medicine for first year medical students, as well as an elective in service learning.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="center-for-health-equity-advancement">Center for Health Equity Advancement&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I currently serve as a postdoctoral Fellow at the
&lt;a href="https://www.pennmedicine.org/about/providing-quality-care/penn-medicine-center-for-health-equity-advancement" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Center for Health Equity Advancement&lt;/a>.I&amp;rsquo;m working with the Center for Health Equity Advancement to understand and reform how race is used (incorrectly) in the pre-clinical and clinical curricula at Penn. These manuscripts are currently in progress. I&amp;rsquo;ve also done work on interventions for social needs and health system interventions into the social and structural determinants of health.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="doctoring-ia">Doctoring IA:&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For several years, I worked with a team to develop and run a course for first year medical students titled Doctoring 1A: Introduction to Medicine and Society. A summary of our initial concept of the course can be found in this article, which describes the philosophy and general structure of the course sessions:
&lt;a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/27680318/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&amp;ldquo;Integrating Theory, Content, and Method to Foster Critical Consciousness in Medical Students: A Comprehensive Model for Cultural Competence Training”&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I have also previously written about
&lt;a href="https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/absolutely-maybe/vulnerability-as-strength-thoughts-on-changing-medicinee28099s-hidden-curriculum/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the hidden curriculum&lt;/a>, the
&lt;a href="https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/absolutely-maybe/histories-our-bodies-tell-experiencing-racism/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">embodiment of racism&lt;/a>, and the
&lt;a href="https://href.li/?http://somatosphere.net/2019/vigilance-as-coping-vigilance-as-injury.html/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">stress of discrimination&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Back to
&lt;a href="/page/my-work/">my work&amp;hellip;&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Refuge</title><link>/page/refuge/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 16:03:50 -0400</pubDate><guid>/page/refuge/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="summary">Summary&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>My dissertation project, &lt;em>Up from the Dirt: Racializing Refuge, Rupture, and Repair in Philadelphia&lt;/em>, was based upon years of ethnographic observation, interviews, and archival research in Philadelphia among organizations that care for and resettle refugees. My dissertation places care for refugees and other humanitarian migrants in political, economic, and social context with a particular emphasis on broader patterns of racial discrimination and state-sanctioned violence. The project explores the intersection of care and governance in Philadelphia through the lens of displacement, beginning with an ethnographic study of refugees and the institutions in Philadelphia that serve them. I analyze Philadelphia as a place formed through migration and displacement, from successive refugee migrations beginning in the 20th century to other movements, like the Great Migration, that have shaped demographic patterns and social life in the city of Brotherly Love. Drawing from a large, diverse archive that brings news, personal narratives &amp;amp; oral histories, and cultural representations both past and present into conversation with semi-structured interviews and ethnographic participant-observation at multiple sites, my work strives to understand what making refuge looks like and for whom asylum is possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My analytic framework draws from literatures about humanitarianism, affect, and the anthropology of the state to understand how refugee resettlement in Philadelphia is inflected with the politics of race, gender, and class. Drawing from feminist theory and queer of color critique, I explore comparative racialization through a framework that recognizes how groups are racialized with respect to one another through competing racial formations at the same time that it accounts for heterogeneity within racial categories. I do so through a particular attentiveness to state bureaucratic processes, from welfare applications to public health management, as they are negotiated by healthcare providers, case workers, and volunteers, not to mention refugees and asylum seekers themselves.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a Black woman, an immigrant, and a future health care provider, I try to think carefully about the social, political, and economic dynamics that shape care and its unintended consequences. I’m also hopeful that in theorizing displacement and refuge, we can reconsider what justice can and should look like for racialized people. Thinking as such might allow us to imagine a reparative politics that offers new possibilities for the future.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="related-articles--other-publications">Related Articles &amp;amp; Other Publications&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>While my dissertation is not currently publicly available, you can read an abstract of the dissertation
&lt;a href="https://href.li/?https://repository.upenn.edu/edissertations/3488/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>. I have also written about my work in other locations, including:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>A more experimental piece, drawing from my experiences as a volunteer with an asylum clinic:
&lt;a href="https://hopkinsmedicalhumanities.org/tendon-magazine/asylum-human-a-meditation-in-8-parts-by-michelle-munyikwa/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">asylum/human: a meditation in 8 parts&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>A research article based on my experiences learning to practice refugee medicine:
&lt;a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/0162243920905014?journalCode=sthd" target="_blank" rel="noopener">“(De)Racializing Refugee Medicine.”&lt;/a> An invited contribution to a special issue of Science, Technology, and Human Values on “Race as a Ghost Variable in Biomedical Research.”&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>An initial piece I worked on before I started writing my dissertation in earnest for
&lt;a href="https://href.li/?http://www.anthropology-news.org/index.php/2017/02/09/racialization-affect-and-refuge/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Anthropology News&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Back to
&lt;a href="/page/my-work/">my work&amp;hellip;&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Teaching</title><link>/page/teaching/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 15:43:58 -0400</pubDate><guid>/page/teaching/</guid><description>&lt;p>I love teaching and mentorship. In my mind, what links my seemingly disparate careers in medicine and anthropology is the centrality and importance of teaching. For me, learning to be an educator is one of the most vital components of being a clinician-scholar: it allows us to both disseminate and produce new knowledge, it provides a pipeline of future scholars, and it is an avenue for justice and equity in research and education. My teaching philosophy draws from my background and training as a future clinician/anthropologist and enables students at several levels (undergraduate, graduate, and medical school) to develop the tools they need to understand complex issues at the intersection of medicine and society.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At the undergraduate level, I have served as a teaching assistant for both large survey courses and small upper-division seminars. I&amp;rsquo;ve also designed courses in medical anthropology at multiple universities. My undergraduate courses emphasize growth and maturation over initial competence, rewarding students for their efforts to become more effective thinkers and writers through low-stakes assignments early in the semester that build confidence and allow learners to acclimate to the challenges of thinking anthropologically. Through in-class exercises like debates and media critiques, we work together as a class to collectively produce knowledge that draws upon their personal experiences of health and healing and contextualizes their narratives within the communities in which they live. Further, learners understand the complexities of caregiving across settings, in particular the unintended consequences of these practices. On my journey to becoming an educator, I&amp;rsquo;ve also taken courses in teaching &amp;amp; pedagogy at the college level.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I developed a similar approach at the medical school level, where I have been involved in course design, implementation, and evaluation for a required course in the medical social sciences. For two years, I served as the Course Liaison for the School of Medicine’s introductory social medicine course,
&lt;a href="/page/health-equity-medical-education/#Doctoring-IA">Doctoring IA: Introduction to Medicine and Society&lt;/a>. As co-director of the course, I selected weekly lecturers and course readings that could appeal to 165 students with varying levels of exposure and interest in the medical humanities and social sciences, social medicine, and public health. Through a certificate in medical education at Penn, I am strengthening my skills as a clinical educator, from the classroom to the wards.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>For copies of my syllabi, please e-mail me.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Overview</title><link>/page/my-work/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 03:32:28 -0400</pubDate><guid>/page/my-work/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="refuge">Refuge:&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>My dissertation project, &lt;em>Up from the Dirt: Racializing Refuge, Rupture, and Repair in Philadelphia&lt;/em>, was based upon years of ethnographic observation, interviews, and archival research in Philadelphia working with organizations that care for and resettle refugees. My dissertation places care for refugees and other humanitarian migrants in political, economic, and social context with a particular emphasis on broader patterns of racial discrimination and state-sanctioned violence.
&lt;a href="/page/refuge/">[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="trauma--inheritance">Trauma &amp;amp; Inheritance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>My second major project, &lt;em>Inheritance&lt;/em>, picks up on the themes of trauma, history, and memory that my first project elaborated. This project will be examining how patients, scholars, and physicians conceptualize the process of inheritance, particularly when it comes to the biological consequences of social inequality. In examining the fields of epigenetics and the embodiment of trauma, I hope to draw upon critical anthropological studies of violence, historical memory, psychoanalysis, and methods in cultural and biocultural anthropology.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="health-equity-and-medical-education">Health Equity and Medical Education&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I also have interests in health equity and medical education. Previously, I helped direct a core course in social medicine for first year medical students, as well as an elective in service learning. I currently serve as a postdoctoral Fellow at the
&lt;a href="https://www.pennmedicine.org/about/providing-quality-care/penn-medicine-center-for-health-equity-advancement" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Center for Health Equity Advancement&lt;/a>. To learn more about my work in health equity and medical education, see
&lt;a href="/page/health-equity-medical-education/">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="human-rights-inand-medicine">Human Rights in/and Medicine&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Other work I have conducted is in human rights, humanitarian practice, and medicine. Currently, I am the co-chair of the
&lt;a href="https://www.phrstudents.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Physicians for Human Rights Student Advisory Board&lt;/a>. I have also worked with the Philadelphia Human Rights Clinic, Doctors 4 Camp Closure, and Doctors for America on projects related to human rights. You can see more about this aspect of my work
&lt;a href="/page/human-rights-and-medicine/">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>